PROFESSOR: So we're going to talk
about the Bellman equations.
They specify in a nice recursive way
what it means to be optimal, or more
generally, what it means to compute
some kind of value that we're
interested in.
And they're pretty simple.
They basically say, there's going to be
one step where you actually write
out your choice.
You actually write out the
Expectimax recurrence.
And then they say, once you're
done with that one step, just
keep on being optimal.
What's that actually mean?
Well, for equations, that gives
rise to a system of equations.
But if we think about that in terms of
implementation, it suggests a kind of
recursive procedure or some kind
of iterative dynamic program.
So what are these Bellman equations?
Well, we'd like to write some kind
of definition of optimal utility.
And we'd like to do it via this notion
of Expectimax, because that's really
what grounds our idea of what
it means to act optimally.
You max when you have a choice over
actions, and when things are out of
your control, you average.
And if you did that computation all
the way down, that would reflect
optimal behavior.
Now of course we can't do
it all the way down.
We're going to do one level.
So let's write this.
Let's write down various quantities
that are going to be optimal.
And let's write it in a way that
encodes what Expectimax does.
So we can first start at the top of the
tree and say, the Expectimax value
of the state--
that's V* for that state.
OK, well, what did Expectimax do?
It says that the optimal value from a
state is achieved by looking at all of
the actions you can take.
And you're going to take a maximum
over all those actions.
Well, what are you going to maximize?
You're going to maximize the
values of the children.
What are the values of the children?
Well, in Expectimax we call
them chance nodes.
Now we call them Q-states.
So we can just write
down their values.
Their values are Q*.
The state hasn't changed yet, because
I haven't actually taken the action.
But I'm considering a
specific action a.
So that's a chance node.
So the value of a state is just the max
of all the chance nodes below it,
which is the max over all of the
Q-states that you can get to, which is
just, we look at all the actions and
then recurse into the Q-values.
Then what happens at a chance node?
How can I write an expression
for the optimal value at a
Q-state or a chance node?
Well, we can think about that.
What happens in Expectimax?
We look at all of the possible outcomes,
s-prime, and we take an
average over them.
So here we're going to have
to take an average.
So we're going to consider all values
s-prime that can occur as a result of
this action, and then we're going to
take an average of those, which is
going to look like a sum.
It's going to have weights which are
given by the transition function.
And then what happens in here?
Well, here we've already committed to
action a, and we're imagining that
s-prime is the outcome.
And we're going to average
over all the s-primes.
Well, what happens?
Well, what happens is two things.
You immediately get an
instantaneous reward.
That's the reward you get this
transition, this step.
And then you land.
And when you land in s-prime, in
Expectimax you would then recurse.
And the way we write that here
is we just plug in V* of s.
The one extra thing we had was we had
a discount, which we didn't have in
vanilla Expectimax, which tells you,
when you recurse, you have to multiply
in this factor of gamma so that
everything lower than you in the tree
contributes less.
So here what we have is kind of mutual
recurrence, if you think about this
like function calls.
But what it really is is a system of
equations, because V* occurs on the
left and the right.
OK, so we have the system of equations
that says optimal values are defined
in terms of optimal Q-values.
That's just the max node.
Optimal Q-values are defined in
terms of optimal values of
the next state, s-prime.
It's a little more complicated, because
we both have to average over
the children--
that takes more time to write
out than just a max--
and because there's two components,
the instantaneous reward from that
timestep and the discounted future.
Together, these are called
the Bellman equations.
And they're usually written
with Q inlined like this.
When you look at this, it's very
easy to go into symbol shock.
But look at this, and whenever you see
this, you think, oh, we're talking
about optimal values.
The optimal value of a state
is like Expectimax.
I max over the action, I average
over the outcomes of the
action, and then I recurse.
And what recursion means is first reward
from the first timestep, and
discounted futures.
So whenever you see this, you
think, oh, that's Expectimax
written one layer out.
So it's only been unrolled one layer and
written as a system of equations.
OK.
These are the Bellman equations.
What do they do?
They characterize the optimal values.
They look a lot like Expectimax, and
I built intuition by calling them
Expectimax-like things.
But in fact, they are not code.
They do not actually recurse.
They are a system of equations.
You plug in values, and if this system
of equations holds, then that's an
optimal set of values.
These equations don't, at least on the
surface, tell you how to compute the
optimal values themselves.
Now we had an algorithm that basically
fixes that for us.
We have the algorithm
of value iteration.
And what value iteration does is it
basically just takes these Bellman
equations which characterize optimal
utilities, and it turns them into a
method of computing them.
So if we think about this idea where the
optimal values, V(s), are defined
in terms of other optimal values which
have been unrolled one level of the
Expectimax, then we got this equation,
where V* appeared on the
left and on the right.
Value iteration, which we talked about
earlier, computes the values simply by
changing the equality sign
into an assignment.
The critical change here was that the
equations have the actual optimal
values on the left and the right, so
there's no real notion of a base case.
For value iteration itself, you
have to start somewhere.
And so what we had was we had a notion
of time-limited, which corresponded to
depth-limited, values.
And so we had this notion of values, not
the actual optimal values but the
optimal values for only k or
k plus 1 more timesteps.
And so the optimal value-- that is, the
score under optimal action for k
plus 1 timesteps--
has on the right-hand side optimal
values for only k timesteps.
And because of this, this
now is a real recursion.
It bottoms out at zero, where
the optimal value for zero
timesteps is zero.
This we could implement.
And the two changes were equality became
an assignment, and suddenly we
had a notion of times attached.
And as k got larger and larger, we
proved that this approached the
optimal values, V*.
So what was value iteration?
Value iteration is just a fixed-point
method of solving
this system of equations.
This system of equations is hard to
solve, because it's got averages and
also maxes.
So it's not a linear thing.
And so we have to solve it somehow.
Value iteration is one way to do it.
Expectimax was really another
way to do it.
And they have a trade-off as to which
one is actually more efficient.
Now in value iteration, the vectors V
sub k themselves were interpretable as
time-limited values.
But you can also view this value
iteration process simply as searching
for a fixed point to these equations
in an iterative way.
And that's a general way of approaching
fixed-point methods.